Guide to the Martha Foster Crawford diaries, 1846-1881 RL.10064
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Martha Foster Crawford diaries
1846-1881
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.10064
1 Linear Feet 7 volumes
Collection contains diaries of Martha (Foster) Crawford as a young woman in Alabama, 1845-1851, and later as a Baptist missionary to China. Topics include conditions in Shanghai from 1852 to 1864 and afterwards at Tengchow, Shantung, and her reactions to the Civil War in the United States. Her diary shows the impact of the American Protestant missionary on China with a day-by-day record of her life. The Shanghai period covers the Taiping rebellion and discusses the hope that the rebellion might furnish a means for converting the Empire to Christianity. Included also are several printed pamphlets and an original manuscript history of missions in China.
Collection Overview
Collection contains diaries of Martha (Foster) Crawford as a young woman in Alabama, 1845-1851, and later as a Baptist missionary to China. Topics include conditions in Shanghai from 1852 to 1864 and afterwards at Tengchow, Shantung, and her reactions to the Civil War in the United States. Her diary shows the impact of the American Protestant missionary on China with a day-by-day record of her life. The Shanghai period covers the Taiping rebellion and discusses the hope that the rebellion might furnish a means for converting the Empire to Christianity. Included also are several printed pamphlets and an original manuscript history of missions in China.
Biographical Note
Martha Foster Crawford was a Baptist missionary and wife of Tarleton Perry Crawford, from Clinton (Greene Co.), Alabama.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Baptists -- China; Missions -- China; Baptists -- Missions -- China; Women -- Religious life -- Southern States.; Women -- Southern States -- Diaries; Women -- Alabama -- Social life and customs; Women missionaries -- China; China -- Civilization -- Christian influences.; China -- Religion; China -- History -- Taiping Rebellion, 1850-1864.; Crawford, Tarleton Perry
- Martha Foster Crawford diaries, 1846-1881
  - Diary, 1846-1850, 1867; 302 pages (Box 2)
  - Diary, 1850-1853, 1878; 229 pages (Box 2)
  - Diary [typed copy], evaluation by Thomas E. Lefargue, 1851-1852; 28 pages (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Note in folder: This typed copy contains many errors - M.R"
  - Diary and loose items from pocket, 1853-1854; 241 pages (Box 1-2)
  - Diary [typed copy], evaluation by Thomas E. Lafargue, 1853-1854; 160 pages (Box 1)
    Note in folder: "This typed copy contains many errors - M.R"
  - Diary, 1861-1864; 121 pages (Box 2)
  - Diary, 1864-1868; 156 pages (Box 2)
  - Diary, 1868-1876; 148 pages (Box 2)
  - Diary [unbound], 1874; 52 pages (Box 2)
  - Diary, 1876-1881; 126 pages (Box 2)